<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Taylors pastorall being both historicall and satyricall: or the noble antiquitie of shepheards, with the profitable vse of sheepe: with a small touch of a scabbed sheepe, and a caueat against that infection.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118298</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853505</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1036:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Taylors pastorall being both historicall and satyricall: or the noble antiquitie of shepheards, with the profitable vse of sheepe: with a small touch of a scabbed sheepe, and a caueat against that infection.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By G[eorge] P[urslowe] for Henrie Gosson, and are to be sold at Edward Wrights shop neere Christs Church Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Taylor.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sheep --  England --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wool --  England --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:1"/>
            <p>Taylors Paſtorall: BEING BOTH HISTORICALL AND SATYRICALL: <hi>Or the</hi> Noble Antiquitie of Shepheards, with the <hi>profitable vſe of Sheepe:</hi> With a ſmall touch of a ſcabbed Sheepe, and a caueat <hi>againſt that infection.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Henrie Goſſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>Edward Wrights</hi> ſhop neere Chriſts Church Gate. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL IVDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIOVS AND TRVLY GENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, my well approued good friend Mr. THOMAS DOVE, Archdeacon of <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, the accompliſhment of his worthy deſires Temporall and Eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ookes without Patrons, are like Babes without Parents, (for except the one be pleaſing and plauſible to humour, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpoſitions of men, and the other left with warme portions or legacies in the tuition of faithfull Executors or Guardians) both Bookes and Babes are happy if they die in their birth, that the firſt minute of their miſerie may be the firſt moment of their felicities: theſe conſiderations haue humbly emboldened me to lay this poore Infant of my laborious Braine, at the doore or gate of your patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage &amp; protection, not doubting but your innated chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, good diſpoſition, and vnfaigned affectation of al Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable endeuours, will giue it both free and hoſpitable
<pb facs="tcp:18889:3"/>entertainment. The function I treate of being venerable and honourable, as of <hi>Shepheards,</hi> the profit commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, lawfull, neceſſarie, ample, and vniuerſall, as of <hi>Sheepe.</hi> The writing or method of it hiſtoricall, myſticall, tropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, typicall, literall, and Satyricall; which hath encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me to dedicate my poore Shepheardly inuention, and their harmleſſe flockes to your Worſhips good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, whoſe reuerend function is truly Paſtorall; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that my many imperfections in writing, and vnworthineſſe in handling ſo worthy a ſubiect, hath made me doubtfull to vſe the protection of your Name; yet on the other ſide, conſidering your good inclination, and mine owne humble innocencie, both my ſelfe and my beſt endeauours I here conſecrate to be employed euer in your Worſhips ſeruice.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>He whoſe meaning, writing, and ſpeaking, are one: IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:3"/>
            <head>All thoſe that will not read this plaine Epiſtle, Lay downe the Booke, on Gods Name, and goe whiſtle.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oneſt mens Sonnes (if I giue you a wrong name, I aske your Fathers pardon) although euery one that eates Mutton, may truely bee ſuſpected for a ſheepe-biter, yet I hope my Sheepe ſhall finde no ſuch dogged dealing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you. There are indeed three ſorts of Creatures, two of which are ſo much repugnant to a Sheepe, that I thinke there will neuer be an vnion betwixt them, which are a Wolfe and a Dog: the third is a Goate, which although they may graze or paſture one with another, as Chriſtians and Infidels are wouen together in the linſey woolſey web of the world, yet I did neuer know any kind of familiarity betweene them. And be thou in nature, a Wolfe, a Dog, or a Goate, that readſt this, I paſſe not, but I rather pitty thy accurſed inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then ſtand in any feare of thy Butting or Byting: the honeſt-minded Reader ſhall finde my Subiect or Theame both laudable and Honourable: and thoſe who hold the name of Shepheard in contempt or deriſion, may heere find truely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that the whole world doth not now containe, nor euer will retaine any men, who for goodneſſe, honour, true worth, worthineſſe and reſpect, that can or dare make compariſon with the Shepheards of former ages. And though <hi>Virgill, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Mantuan,</hi> and many of our learned Engliſh and Scottiſh Poets, haue made their inuentions trauell vp the top of the
<pb facs="tcp:18889:4"/>forked Mountaine of <hi>Parnaſſus;</hi> yet I would haue the Reader know, that if they, each of them had <hi>Argos</hi> eyes, to ſuruay and obſerue, and as many hands as <hi>Briareus,</hi> to write, yet for all their paines, diligent ſearch and collections, my weake capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie can find matter enough to make an honeſt Pamphlet out of what they haue ouerſeene, neglected, or made ſlight account of. Foure things, I haue, doe, and euer will obſerue in my Writings; which are, not to write prophane, obſceane, palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and odious Lyes, or ſcandalous Libels. In keeping which Decorum, I hope I ſhall keepe my ſelfe within the limits or bounds of good mens Reſpect. And this Aduertiſement more I giue the Reader, that there are many things Imprinted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of two Letters, <hi>I. T.</hi> for ſome of which I haue beene taxed to be the Author: I aſsure the world that I had neuer any thing imprinted of my writing, that I was either afraid or aſhamed to ſet my name at large to it; and therefore if you ſee any Authors name <hi>I. T.</hi> I vtterly diſclaime it: for I am as I haue bin, both <hi>I.</hi> and <hi>T.</hi> which with addition of Letters, is yours to be commanded in any laudable endeuours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN TAYLOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:4"/>
            <head>Taylors Paſtorall, being both <hi>Hiſtoricall and Satyricall.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>APollo</hi> (father of the Siſters nine,</l>
               <l>I craue thy aide t'inſpire this Muſe of mine,</l>
               <l>Thou that thy golden Glory didſt lay by</l>
               <l>(As <hi>Ouid</hi> doth relate moſt wittily)</l>
               <l>And in a Shepheards ſhape, didſt deigne to keepe</l>
               <l>Thy Loues beloued Sire, <hi>Admetus ſheepe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And rurall <hi>Pan,</hi> thy helpe I doe intreate,</l>
               <l>That (to the life) the praiſe I may repeate</l>
               <l>Of the contented life, and mightie ſtockes</l>
               <l>Of happy <hi>Shepheards,</hi> and their harmleſſe flockes.</l>
               <l>But better thoughts my Errors doe controule</l>
               <l>For an offence, moſt negligent and foule,</l>
               <l>In thus inuoking, like a heathen man,</l>
               <l>Helpe, helpleſſe, from <hi>Apollo,</hi> or from <hi>Pan:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When as the ſubiect, which I haue in hand,</l>
               <l>Is almoſt infinite, as ſtarres, or ſand,</l>
               <l>Grac'd with Antiquitie, vpon Record</l>
               <l>In the Eternall, neuer-failing Word.</l>
               <l>There 'tis ingrauen true and manifeſt,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Shepheards,</hi> were both beſt and bleſt.</l>
               <l>I therefore inuocate the gracious aide</l>
               <l>Of Thee, whoſe mightie Word hath all things made,</l>
               <l>I <hi>Iſraels</hi> great <hi>Shepheard</hi> humbly craue</l>
               <l>That his aſſur'd aſſiſtance I may haue:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:5"/>
               <l>That my vnlearned Muſe no verſe compile,</l>
               <l>Which may be impious, prophane or vile,</l>
               <l>And though through Ignorance, or negligence,</l>
               <l>My poore inuention fall into offence,</l>
               <l>I doe implore that boundleſſe Grace of his,</l>
               <l>Not ſtrictly to regard what is amiſſe:</l>
               <l>But vnto me belongeth all the blame,</l>
               <l>And all the Glory be vnto his Name.</l>
               <l>Yet as this Booke is verſe, ſo men muſt know,</l>
               <l>I muſt ſome Fictions and Alluſions ſhow,</l>
               <l>Some ſhreds, ſowe remnants, reliques, or ſome ſcraps,</l>
               <l>The Muſes may inſpire me with perhaps,</l>
               <l>Which taken literally, as lies may ſeeme,</l>
               <l>And ſo miſ-vnderſtanding may miſdeeme.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Sheepe</hi> therefore, before to worke I fall,</l>
               <l>Ile ſhew the <hi>Shepheards</hi> firſt originall:</l>
               <l>Thoſe that the beſt Records will reade and marke,</l>
               <l>Shall finde iuſt <hi>Abel</hi> was a Patriarke,<note place="margin">Abel, a Prince, a Patriarke, a figure of the true Church, a type of Chriſt, &amp; a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard. Abraham a Prince, a Patriarke, intituled with the Glorious title of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull, a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Our father <hi>Adams</hi> ſecond ſonne, a Prince,</l>
               <l>(As great as any man begotten ſince)</l>
               <l>Yet in his function he a <hi>Shepheard</hi> was:</l>
               <l>And ſo his mortall pilgrimage did paſſe.</l>
               <l>And in the ſacred Text it is compilde,</l>
               <l>That he that's father of the faithfull ſtilde,</l>
               <l>Did as a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> liue vpon th'encreaſe</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Sheepe,</hi> vntill his daies on earth did ceaſe.</l>
               <l>And in thoſe times it was apparent then</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Abram</hi> both were noble men:</l>
               <l>The one obtain'd the title <hi>righteouſly</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For his vnfeigned ſeruing the moſt HIGH,</l>
               <l>He firſt did offer <hi>Sheepe,</hi> which (on Record)</l>
               <l>Was ſacrifice accepted of the Lord.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:5"/>
               <l>He was (before the infant world was ripe)</l>
               <l>The Churches figure, and his Sauiours type.</l>
               <l>A murdered Martyr, who for ſeruing God,</l>
               <l>Did firſt of all feele perſecutions rod.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Abraham</hi> was in account ſo great,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abimelech</hi> his friendſhip did intreate.</l>
               <l>Faiths paterne, and Obedience ſample, he</l>
               <l>Like ſtarres, or ſand, was in poſteritie:</l>
               <l>In him the Nations of the earth were bleſt,<note place="margin">Iſack.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And now his boſome figures heau'nly REST.</l>
               <l>His <hi>Sheepe</hi> almoſt paſt numbring multiplide,</l>
               <l>And when (as he thought) <hi>Iſaack</hi> ſhould haue dide,</l>
               <l>Then by th'Almighties Mercies, Loue, and Grace</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sheepe</hi> from out a Buſh ſupplide the place.<note place="margin">Let a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lot</hi> was a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> (<hi>Abrams</hi> brothers ſonne)</l>
               <l>And ſuch great fauour from his God he wonne,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Sodom</hi> could not be conſum'd with fire,</l>
               <l>Till he and his did out of it retire,</l>
               <l>They felt no vengeance for their foule offence,</l>
               <l>Till righteous <hi>Let</hi> was quite departed thence.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iacob,</hi> as the holy Ghoſt doth tell,<note place="margin">Iacob.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Who afterwards was called <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who wraſtled with his God, and (to his fame)</l>
               <l>Obtain'd a <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>Bleſsing</hi> for the ſame,</l>
               <l>He (vnder <hi>Laban</hi>) was a Shepheard long,</l>
               <l>And ſuffred from him much ingratefull wrong,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Rachel</hi> and for <hi>Leah,</hi> he did beare</l>
               <l>The yoke of ſeruitude full twentie yeare,</l>
               <l>He was a Patriarke, a Prince of might,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wealth in ſheepe, was almoſt infinite,</l>
               <l>His twice ſixe ſonnes (as holy writ deſcribes,</l>
               <l>Who were the famous fathers, of twelue tribes)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:6"/>
               <l>Were for the moſt part Shepheards, and ſuch men</l>
               <l>Whoſe like the world ſhall ner'e containe agen.</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> 'mongſt the reſt, eſpecially,</l>
               <l>A conſtant mirrour of true Chaſtity:</l>
               <l>Who was in his affliction, of behauiour</l>
               <l>A mortall <hi>Type</hi> of his immortall Sauiour:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Truth</hi> his mother <hi>Rachel</hi> doth expreſſe</l>
               <l>To be her father <hi>Labans</hi> Shepheardeſſe.<note place="margin">Rachel.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Meeke <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Moſes.</note> whom the Lord of hoſts did call</l>
               <l>To leade his people out of <hi>Egypts</hi> thrall,</l>
               <l>Whoſe power was ſuch, as no mans was before,</l>
               <l>Nor ſince his time hath any mans beene more,</l>
               <l>Yet in the ſacred text it plaine appeares,</l>
               <l>That he was <hi>Iethroes</hi> Shepheard fortie yeares.</l>
               <l>Heroicke <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dauid.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſhayes</hi> youngeſt ſonne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe acts immortall memorie hath wonne:</l>
               <l>Whoſe valiant vigour did in pieces teare</l>
               <l>A furious Lion and a rauenous Beare:</l>
               <l>Who (arm'd with faith and fortitude alone)</l>
               <l>Slew great <hi>Goliah,</hi> with a ſling and ſtone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe victories the people ſung moſt plaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> hath a thouſand, <hi>He</hi> ten thouſand ſlaine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> from the ſheepfold came to be a King,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fame for euer through the world ſhall ring:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> was another Type of that bleſt HE</l>
               <l>That <hi>was,</hi> and <hi>is,</hi> and euermore ſhall be.</l>
               <l>His vertuous Acts are writ for imitation,</l>
               <l>His holy Hymnes and Pſalmes for conſolation,</l>
               <l>For Reprehenſion and for Contemplation,</l>
               <l>And finally to ſhew vs our ſaluation,</l>
               <l>The Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos.</note> vnto whom the Lord</l>
               <l>Reueald the ſacred ſecrets of his Word:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:6"/>
               <l>God raiſd him from the ſheepfold, to foretell</l>
               <l>What plagues ſhould fall on ſinfull <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>True Patience paterne, Prince of his affections,<note place="margin">Iob.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Moſt mightie tamer of his imperfections,</l>
               <l>Whoſe guard was God, whoſe guide the holy Ghoſt.</l>
               <l>Bleſt in his wealth, of which <hi>Sheepe</hi> was the moſt.</l>
               <l>Iuſt <hi>Iobs</hi> loſt riches doubled was agen,<note place="margin">Seth and Noah, were ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards &amp; feeders of cattell.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Who liu'd belou'd of God, admir'd of men.</l>
               <l>The firſt of happy tidings on the earth,</l>
               <l>Of our all onely Sauiours bleſſed birth,</l>
               <l>The glorious Angels to the <hi>Shepheards</hi> told,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Luke</hi> th'Euangeliſt doth well vnfold.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhould my verſe a little but decline</l>
               <l>To humane ſtories, and leaue diuine:</l>
               <l>There are ſome mightie Princes I can name,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breeding (at the firſt) from <hi>Shepheards</hi> came.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romes</hi> founder <hi>(Romulus)</hi> was bred and fed,<note place="margin">Romulus.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Mongſt <hi>Shepheards,</hi> where his youthfull daies he led.<note place="margin">Valerius Maximus and Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus were raiſd from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine. Pſal. 80.1.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch <hi>(Cyrus)</hi> he did paſſe</l>
               <l>His youth with <hi>Shepheards,</hi> and a <hi>Shepheard</hi> was,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Terrour</hi> of the world, that famous man</l>
               <l>Who conquer'd Kings, and kingdomes ouer-ran</l>
               <l>His ſtile was, (as ſome ſtories do repeate)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Scythian Shepheard, Tamberlaine</hi> the great.</l>
               <l>Tis ſuch a title of preeminence,</l>
               <l>Of reuerence, and ſuch high magnificence,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Dauid,</hi> (who ſo well his words did frame)</l>
               <l>Did call our great Creator by that name.</l>
               <l>Our bleſt <hi>Redeemer</hi> (<hi>Gods</hi> eternall <hi>Sonne</hi>)</l>
               <l>Whoſe onely merits our ſaluation wonne.</l>
               <l>He did the harmleſſe name of <hi>Shepheard</hi> take</l>
               <l>For our protection, and his mercies ſake.<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.11, 12.</note>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:7"/>
               <l>Thoſe that will reade the ſacred Text, and looke</l>
               <l>With diligence, throughout that heauenly Booke,</l>
               <l>Shall finde the <hi>Miniſters</hi> haue Epethites,</l>
               <l>And named <hi>Angels, Stewards, Watchmen, Lights,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salt, Builders, Husbandmen,</hi> and <hi>Starres</hi> that ſhine,</l>
               <l>(Inflamed with the <hi>Light</hi> which is <hi>Diuine</hi>)</l>
               <l>And with theſe names, within that Booke compilde,</l>
               <l>They with the Stile of Shepheards are inſtilde.</l>
               <l>Thus God the Sire, and Sonne, the Scriptures call</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Shepheards,</hi> myſticall and litterall,</l>
               <l>And by ſimilitudes comparing to,</l>
               <l>All Kings and Churchmen beare that title do.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18889:7"/>
            <head>A. E. I. O. V. two Anagrams of the fiue vowels, the one ſerues for the glorious name of God, and the other in the Spaniſh tongue is a Sheepe, which name the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> doth figuratiuely or myſtically call our Creator IEOVA, or IEHOVAH, OVEIA, is a Sheepe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein may be perceiued, that there is no word, name or action, in or vnder Heauen, but hath one or more of the fiue vowels, and that no word or Name hath them <hi>all without other Letters, but</hi> IEOVA, <hi>and</hi> OVEIA. <hi>Which doth admoniſh vs in the feare and reuerence of the Almightie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all our thoughts, words and actions, ſome part of his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Name is infinitely included. And withall that</hi> OVEIA <hi>or a Sheepe is a moſt ſignificant Emblem, or ſigne of our God and Sauiours innocencie and patient ſuffrings.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WIſe and Inſcrutable, Omniſcient,</l>
               <l>Eternall, Gracious, and Omnipotent,</l>
               <l>In Loue, in Iuſtice, Mercie and in Might,</l>
               <l>In Honour, Power and Glory infinite,</l>
               <l>In workes, in words, in euery Attribute</l>
               <l>Almightie, All-commanding, Abſolute;</l>
               <l>For who ſo notes the Letters of the name</l>
               <l>IEHOVAH, ſhall perceiue within the ſame,</l>
               <l>The Vowels of all Tongues included be:</l>
               <l>So hath no name that e're was nam'd but He.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:8"/>
               <l>And I haue heard ſome Schollers make Relation,</l>
               <l>That H, is but a breathing Aſpiration;</l>
               <l>A letter that may be left out and ſpar'd,</l>
               <l>Whereby is cleerly to our ſight declar'd,</l>
               <l>That Great IEOVA may be written true</l>
               <l>With onely Vowels, A, E, I, O, V.:</l>
               <l>And that there is no word or name but this,</l>
               <l>That hath them all Alone, but onely His.</l>
               <l>So that the Heauens with all the mighty Hoſt</l>
               <l>Of Creatures there, Earth, Sea, or any Coaſt,</l>
               <l>Or Climate, any Fiſh, or Fowle, or Beaſt,</l>
               <l>Or any of <hi>His</hi> workes, the moſt and leaſt,</l>
               <l>Or thoughts, or words, or writing with the pen,</l>
               <l>Or deeds that are accompliſhed by men,</l>
               <l>But haue ſome of theſe Letters in them all,</l>
               <l>And God alone hath all in Generall.</l>
               <l>By which we ſee, according to his will,</l>
               <l>He is in all things, and doth all things fill,</l>
               <l>And all things ſaid or done, he hath ordain'd,</l>
               <l>Some part of his great Name's therein contain'd;</l>
               <l>All future, preſent, and all paſt things ſeeing,</l>
               <l>In whom we liue, and moue, and haue our being.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A <hi>Almightie, All</hi> in <hi>All,</hi> and euery where,</l>
               <l>E <hi>Eternall,</hi> in whom change cannot appeare,</l>
               <l>I <hi>Immortall,</hi> who made all things mortall elſe,</l>
               <l>O <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> whoſe Power all Power excels,</l>
               <l>V <hi>Vnited,</hi> Three in one, and one in three,</l>
               <l>IEOVA: Vnto whom All Glory bee.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:8"/>
               <l>Beſides the learned Poets of all times,</l>
               <l>Haue chanted out the praiſe, in pleaſant rimes,</l>
               <l>The harmleſſe liues of rurall ſhepheards Swaines,</l>
               <l>And beauteous ſhepheardeſſes on the plaines,<note place="margin">All the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets and Poeteſſes of altongs and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, haue written vpon this worthy ſubiect.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Odes,</hi> in <hi>Roundelaies,</hi> and <hi>Madrigals,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Sonnets,</hi> and in well-pen'd <hi>Paſtorals:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They haue recorded, moſt delightfully,</l>
               <l>Their loues, their fortunes, and felicitie,</l>
               <l>And ſure, if in this low terreſtriall Round</l>
               <l>Plaine honeſt happineſſe is to be found;</l>
               <l>It with the <hi>Shepheards</hi> is remaining ſtill,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they haue leaſt power to doe ill:</l>
               <l>And whilſt they on their feeding flockes attend,</l>
               <l>They haue the leaſt occaſions to offend.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambition, Pompe,</hi> and hell-begotten <hi>Pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And damned <hi>Adulation,</hi> they deride:</l>
               <l>The complementall flattry of Kings Courts,</l>
               <l>Is neuer intermix'd amidſt their ſports;</l>
               <l>They ſeldome enuy at each others ſtate,</l>
               <l>Their loue and feare is Gods, the deuil's their hate.</l>
               <l>In weightie buſineſſe they nor marre or make,</l>
               <l>And curſed bribes they neither giue or take.</l>
               <l>They are not guiltie (as ſome great men are)</l>
               <l>T'vndoe their Mercer and Embroiderer,</l>
               <l>Their Tailer, Butcher, Brewer, Baker, Powlter,</l>
               <l>(For which there's ſome haue well deſeru'd a halter)</l>
               <l>Their Shoemaker and Silkeman I forgot,</l>
               <l>Though breaking, or elſe begg'ry be their lot,</l>
               <l>Nor is't a ſhepheards trade, by night or day</l>
               <l>To ſweare themſelues in debt, and neuer pay.</l>
               <l>He's no ſtate-plotting <hi>Machiuilian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or Proiect-monger Monopolitan:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:9"/>
               <l>He hath no trickes or wiles to circumuent,</l>
               <l>Nor feares he when there comes a Parlament.</l>
               <l>He neuer weares his cap, or bends his knee</l>
               <l>To feed contention with a Lawyers fee:</l>
               <l>He wants the art to Cogge, Cheate, Sweare and Lie,</l>
               <l>Nor feares the Gallowes, or the Pillorie.</l>
               <l>Nor cares he if great men be fooles or wiſe,</l>
               <l>If honour fall, and baſe diſhonour riſe,</l>
               <l>Let fortunes mounted minions ſinke or ſwim,</l>
               <l>He neuer breakes his braines, all's one to him.</l>
               <l>He's free from feare full curſes of the poore,</l>
               <l>And liu's and dies content,<note place="margin">Great te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance in Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard.</note> with leſſe, or more.</l>
               <l>He doth not waſte the time, as many vſe,</l>
               <l>His good Creators creatures to abuſe,</l>
               <l>In drinking ſicke vngodly healths to ſome,</l>
               <l>The verieſt Cankerwormes of Chriſtendome:</l>
               <l>My Lord <hi>Ambition,</hi> and my Lady <hi>Pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall with his quaffing, not be magnifide:</l>
               <l>Nor for their ſakes will he carowſe and feaſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill (from man) he be turn'd worſe then beaſt.</l>
               <l>Whereby he ſcapes vaine oathes, and blaſphemy,</l>
               <l>And ſurfets, (fruits of drunken gluttony.)</l>
               <l>He ſcapes occaſion vnto luſts pretence,</l>
               <l>And ſo eſcapes the Pox, by conſequence.</l>
               <l>Thus doth he ſcape the Parrator and Proctor,</l>
               <l>Th'Apothecarie, Surgeon, and Doctor;</l>
               <l>Whereby he this prerogatiue may haue,</l>
               <l>To hold the laying in,<note place="margin">Theſe are great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges though few men ſeeke or care for them.</note> into his graue,</l>
               <l>Whilſt many, that his betters farre haue bin,</l>
               <l>Will very hardly hold the laying in.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Shepheards</hi> liue, and thus they end their liues,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd and grac'd with theſe prerogatiues:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:9"/>
               <l>And when he dies, he leaues no wrangling heirs</l>
               <l>To law till all be ſpent, and nothing theirs,</l>
               <l>Hooke, Tar-box, Bottle, Bag, Pipe, Dog, and all</l>
               <l>Shall breed no iarres in Weſtminſters great hall:</l>
               <l>Peace and tranquillitie was all his life,</l>
               <l>And (dead) his goods ſhall be no cauſe of ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Shepheards</hi> haue no places, meanes, or times,</l>
               <l>To fall into thoſe hell-deſeruing crimes,</l>
               <l>Which Courtiers, Lawyers, Tradeſmen, men of Armes</l>
               <l>Commit, vnto their ſoules and bodies harmes.</l>
               <l>And from the <hi>Shepheards</hi> now Ile turne my ſtile</l>
               <l>To ſundry ſorts of <hi>Sheepe</hi> another while.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lambs</hi> that in the Iewes Paſſoeuer di'd,</l>
               <l>Were figures of the <hi>Lambe</hi> that's crucifi'd.<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.7. 1. Ioh 1.29 and Reue. 5.8.9.13.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Eſay</hi> doth compare our heauenly food</l>
               <l>T'a <hi>Sheepe,</hi> which dumb before the ſhearer ſtood:</l>
               <l>Whoſe death, and merits, did this title win,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lambe</hi> of God, which freed the world from ſin.</l>
               <l>LAMBE Anagram's BLAME.</l>
               <l>LAMBE Anagram's BALME.</l>
               <l>The Anagram's of <hi>Lambe</hi> is <hi>Blame</hi> and <hi>Balme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Lambe,</hi> vpon him tooke our <hi>Blame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His precious <hi>Blood,</hi> (Gods heauy wrath did <hi>calme</hi>)</l>
               <l>'T was th'onely <hi>Balme</hi> for <hi>Sinne</hi> to cure the ſame:</l>
               <l>All power, and praiſe, and glory, be therefore</l>
               <l>Aſcribed to the <hi>Lambe</hi> for euermore.</l>
               <l>And in the threeſcore nineteenth Pſalme we reade,</l>
               <l>That like a <hi>Sheepe</hi> our God doth <hi>Ioſeph</hi> leade.</l>
               <l>Againe, of vs he ſuch account doth keepe,</l>
               <l>That of his Paſture we are called <hi>Sheepe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And euery day we doe confeſſe (almoſt)</l>
               <l>That we haue err'd and ſtraid like <hi>Sheepe</hi> that's loſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:10"/>
               <l>Our Sauiour, (that hath bought our ſoules ſo deare)</l>
               <l>Hath ſaid, his <hi>Sheepe</hi> his voice will onely heare:</l>
               <l>And thrice did <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnto Saint <hi>Peter</hi> call,</l>
               <l>(In which he ſpake to his Diſciples all)</l>
               <l>If you doe loue me,<note place="margin">Ioh. 21.15, 16, 17.</note> feed my <hi>Sheepe</hi> (quoth he)</l>
               <l>And feed my <hi>Lambs</hi> well, if you doe loue me.</l>
               <l>Moreouer, in the finall Iudgement day,</l>
               <l>There is the right hand, and the left hand way,</l>
               <l>Whereas the ſheepe he to himſelfe doth gather,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With ſaying, Come, ye bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And to the Goates, in his conſuming ire,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He bids, Depart into eternall fire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus our Redeemer, and his whole elect,</l>
               <l>The name of <hi>Sheepe</hi> held euer in reſpect,</l>
               <l>And the compariſon holds reference</l>
               <l>To profit, and to harmeleſſe innocence.</l>
               <l>For of all beaſts that euer were, or are,</l>
               <l>None can (for goodneſſe) with a <hi>Sheepe</hi> compare:</l>
               <l>Indeed, for bone and burthen I muſt grant,</l>
               <l>He's much inferiour to the Elephant,</l>
               <l>The Dromedarie, Camell, Horſe, and Aſſe,</l>
               <l>For loade and carriage doth a Sheepe ſurpaſſe:</l>
               <l>Strong <hi>Taurus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An Oxe is the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch ſon of a Bull.</note> Eunuch ſonne, the labouring Oxe,</l>
               <l>The ſtately Stagge, the bobtaild craftie Foxe,</l>
               <l>Theſe, and all rauenous beaſts of prey, muſt yeeld</l>
               <l>Vnto the <hi>Sheepe,</hi> the honour of the field.</l>
               <l>I could recount the names of many more,</l>
               <l>The Lion, Vnicorne, the Beare and Bore:</l>
               <l>The Wolfe, the Tiger, the Rhinoſcerot,</l>
               <l>The Leopard, and a number more I wot:</l>
               <l>But all theſe greedy beaſts, great <hi>Ouid,</hi> pen</l>
               <l>Doth ſay are metamorphoſde into men,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:10"/>
               <l>For beaſt to beaſt afford more conſcience can,</l>
               <l>And much leſſe crueltie, than man to man.</l>
               <l>Ile therefore let ſuch beaſts be as they be,</l>
               <l>For feare they kicke, and ſnap, and ſnarle at me.</l>
               <l>Vnto the Sheepe againe my Muſe doth flie,</l>
               <l>For honeſt ſafetie, and commoditie.</l>
               <l>He with his fleſh and fleece, doth feed and clad</l>
               <l>All languages and nations, good and bad:</l>
               <l>What can it more, but die, that we may liue,</l>
               <l>And euery yeare to vs a liuerie giue?</l>
               <l>'Tis ſuch a bountie, and the charge ſo deepe,</l>
               <l>That nothing can affoord the like, but <hi>Sheepe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſhould the world want <hi>Sheepe,</hi> but fiue whole yeare,</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand millions would want cloaths to weare:</l>
               <l>And wert't not for the fleſh of this kinde beaſt,</l>
               <l>The world: might faſt, when it doth often feaſt.</l>
               <l>There's nothing doth vnto a <hi>Sheepe</hi> pertaine,</l>
               <l>But 'tis for mans commoditie and gaine:</l>
               <l>For men to men ſo much vntruſtie are,</l>
               <l>To lie, to couſen, to forſweare and ſweare:</l>
               <l>That oathes, and paſſing words, and ioyning hands,</l>
               <l>Is like aſſurance written in the ſands,</l>
               <l>To make men keepe their words, and mend all this,<note place="margin">Parchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t made of Sheepskin</note>
               </l>
               <l>The ſilly <hi>Sheepe-skin</hi> turn'd to Parchment is.</l>
               <l>There's many a wealthy man, whoſe whole eſtate</l>
               <l>Lies more in Parchment, then in coine or plate,</l>
               <l>Indentures, Leaſes, Euidences, Wills,</l>
               <l>Bonds, Contracts, Records, Obligations, Bills,</l>
               <l>With theſe (although the <hi>Sheepe-skin</hi> is but weake)</l>
               <l>It bindes men ſtrongly that they dare not breake.</l>
               <l>But if a man eates Spiders now and then,</l>
               <l>The oyle of <hi>Parchment</hi> cures him oft agen.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:11"/>
               <l>And what rare ſtuffes which in the world are fram'd,</l>
               <l>Can be in value, like to parchment nam'd;</l>
               <l>The richeſt cloth of gold that can be found,</l>
               <l>A yard of it was ne're worth fiftie pound:</l>
               <l>And I haue ſeene two foot of <hi>Sheepeskin</hi> dreſt,</l>
               <l>Which hath beene worth ten thouſand pounds at leaſt.</l>
               <l>A piece of parchment well with Inke lac'd ouer,</l>
               <l>Helps many a gallant to a Sattin couer:</l>
               <l>Into the Mercer it ſome <hi>Faith</hi> doth ſtrike,</l>
               <l>It giues the Silkeman <hi>Hope</hi> of no diſlike:<note place="margin">If the Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Bill be out of meaſure to the Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then he can make a fit mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for him with his owne bond.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Taylor it with <hi>Charitie</hi> aſſailes,</l>
               <l>It thruſts him laſt betwixt his <hi>Bill</hi> and <hi>Vailes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And by theſe meanes, a piece of parchment can</l>
               <l>Patch vp, and make a Gull a Gentleman.</l>
               <l>The nature of it very ſtrange I finde,</l>
               <l>'Tis much like phiſicke, it can looſe and binde:</l>
               <l>'Tis one mans freedome, and anothers nooſe,</l>
               <l>And like the Pope it doth both binde and looſe.</l>
               <l>And as the <hi>Ram</hi> and <hi>Ewe</hi> doe fructifie,</l>
               <l>And euery yeere a Lambe doth multiplie:</l>
               <l>So doth a ſheepe-skin Bond make money breed</l>
               <l>And procreate, as ſeed doth ſpring from ſeed.</l>
               <l>An hundred pound's the <hi>Ewe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Bond is the Ewe, the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower and lender are both Rams and the Intereſt is the Lamb.</note> which euery yeere</l>
               <l>Doth breed a ten pound <hi>Lambe,</hi> (all charges cleere.)</l>
               <l>Thus is a ſheepe-skin proou'd the onely <hi>Tie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſtay, whereon a world of men relie,</l>
               <l>Which holds a crue of Earthwormes in more awe,</l>
               <l>Then both the Tables of the ſacred Law.</l>
               <l>Paſt number, I could many functions name</l>
               <l>Who (as 'tis parchment) liue vpon the ſame:</l>
               <l>But 'tis ſufficient, this ſmall homely touch:</l>
               <l>Should all be writ, my Booke would ſwell too much.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:11"/>
               <l>Now of the <hi>Ram,</hi> the <hi>Ewe,</hi> the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and <hi>Weather,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile touch their skins as they are turn'd to Leather,</l>
               <l>And made in Purſes, Powches, Laces, Strings,</l>
               <l>Gloues, Points, Booke-Couers, and ten thouſand things,</l>
               <l>And many tradeſmen liue and thriue thereby,</l>
               <l>Which if I would, I more could amplifie.</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Guts</hi> ſerue Inſtruments which ſweetly ſound,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Dung</hi> is beſt to make moſt fruitfull ground:</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Hoofes</hi> burnt, will moſt venom'd ſerpents kill,</l>
               <l>Their grated <hi>Hornes</hi> are good gainſt poyſon ſtill:</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Milke</hi> makes Cheeſe, mans hunger to preuent,</l>
               <l>As I haue ſeene in <hi>Suſsex</hi> and in <hi>Kent:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their <hi>Trotters,</hi> for the healthy or the ſicke,</l>
               <l>(Dreſt as they ſhould be) are good meat to picke.</l>
               <l>The Cookes and Butchers with the <hi>ioints</hi> doe gaine,</l>
               <l>And poore folkes eat the Gather, Head, and Braine;</l>
               <l>And though all wiſe mens iudgement will allow</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sheepe</hi> to be much leſſer then a Cow.</l>
               <l>Yet in a Leg of Mutton I can ſee</l>
               <l>More meat then in a Leg of Beefe can be.</l>
               <l>A liue <hi>Sheepe</hi> hath one Necke, yet I perceiue</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sheepe</hi> being dead, two Neckes of Mutton haue.</l>
               <l>Foure legges each liuing <hi>Sheepe</hi> hath, but once ſlaine,</l>
               <l>(Although he loſe none, yet) he hath but twaine.</l>
               <l>Now, for the honour of the valiant <hi>Ram,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If I were learn'd more treble then I am,</l>
               <l>Yet could I not ſufficiently expreſſe</l>
               <l>His wondrous worth, and worthineſſe.</l>
               <l>For by Aſtronomers 'tis verifide</l>
               <l>How that the <hi>Ram</hi> in heau'n is ſtellifide,<note place="margin">Aries.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And (of the twelue) is plac'd head ſigne of all,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Sol</hi> keepes firſt his Equinoctiall.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:12"/>
               <l>For,<note place="margin">Taurus. Gemini. Cancer. Leo. Virgo. Lybra. Scorpio. Sagitarius Capricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Aquarius. Piſces.</note> hauing at the <hi>Bull</hi> drunke <hi>Aprils</hi> ſhowres,</l>
               <l>And with the <hi>Twins, May</hi> deck'd the earth with flowres:</l>
               <l>And ſcorch'd the <hi>Crab</hi> in <hi>Iune</hi> with burning beames,</l>
               <l>Made <hi>Iulies Lion</hi> chafe with fierie gleames:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Auguſt</hi> ſolace to the <hi>Virgin</hi> giuen</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ballance</hi> in <hi>September</hi> made Time euen,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Octobers Scorpion</hi> with declining courſe,</l>
               <l>And paſſing by <hi>Decembers Archers</hi> force,</l>
               <l>Then hauing paſt <hi>Nouembers</hi> frozen <hi>Goate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He next to <hi>Ianus Waterie Signe</hi> doth floate:</l>
               <l>He to the <hi>Lenten Signe</hi> in <hi>Februarie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſo bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> ends his yeeres vagarie.</l>
               <l>Then, to the <hi>Ram,</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> in his careere,</l>
               <l>He mounts, on which this Sonnet's written heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Sonnet.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>DIurnall <hi>Titans</hi> all-reuiuing Carre,</l>
                  <l>Throughout the heau'ns his progreſſe 'gins to take:</l>
                  <l>And now his gliſtring Raies he doth vnbarre,</l>
                  <l>What abſence marr'd, his preſence now doth make:</l>
                  <l>Now he begins Earths mourning face to drie</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Eols</hi> breath, and his bright heauenly heate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>March</hi> duſt (like clouds) through aire doth march &amp; flie:</l>
                  <l>Dead-ſeeming Trees and Plants new life doth get.</l>
                  <l>Thus when the <hi>Worlds eie dazler</hi> takes his Inne</l>
                  <l>At the celeſtiall <hi>Ram,</hi> then Winter's done:</l>
                  <l>And then dame Nature doth her liuerie ſpinne</l>
                  <l>Of flowers and fruits, which all the Earth puts on.</l>
                  <l>Thus when <hi>Apollo</hi> doth to <hi>Aries</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>The Earth is freed from Winters martyrdome.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:12"/>
                  <l>Thus haue I prou'd the Ram a luckie ſigne,</l>
                  <l>Wherein Heau'n, Earth, and Sunne and Aire combine,</l>
                  <l>To haue their vniuerſall comforts hurld</l>
                  <l>Vpon the face of the decaying world.</l>
                  <l>With twelue ſignes each mans bodie's gouerned,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Aries,</hi> or the <hi>Ram,</hi> doth rule the head,<note place="margin">To be cald Ramhead, is a title of honour &amp; a name proper to all men.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then are their iudgements fooliſh, fond, and baſe,</l>
                  <l>That take the name of <hi>Ramhead</hi> in diſgrace;</l>
                  <l>'Tis honour for the head to haue the name</l>
                  <l>Deriued from the <hi>Ram</hi> that rules the ſame:</l>
                  <l>And that the <hi>Ram</hi> doth rule the head, I know,</l>
                  <l>For euery Almanacke the ſame doth ſhow.</l>
                  <l>He that ſells wood, is call'd a Woodmonger;</l>
                  <l>He that ſells fiſh, is call'd a Fiſhmonger;</l>
                  <l>He that doth brew, is call'd a Brewer; and</l>
                  <l>He's call'd a Landlord that takes rent for land;</l>
                  <l>He that bakes Bread, ſcornes not the name of Baker;<note place="margin">The ſtare will haue it ſo.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He that makes Cuckolds, is a Cuckold-maker.</l>
                  <l>So as the <hi>Ram</hi> doth rule the head, I ſee,</l>
                  <l>By Conſtellation, all men Ramheads be.</l>
                  <l>And as the twelue Celeſtiall ſignes beare ſway,</l>
                  <l>And with their motions paſſe mans life away:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ram,</hi> the head, the <hi>Bull,</hi> the necke and throte,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Twins,</hi> ſhoulders, <hi>Crab</hi> doth rule the breſt, I note,<note place="margin">A comfort for Cuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olds, that though a man hath a Rame head, yet he hath a Lions heart.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But 'tis the <hi>Lions</hi> portion, and his part,</l>
                  <l>To be the valiant ruler of the heart.</l>
                  <l>From whence ſuch men may gather this reliefe,</l>
                  <l>That though a <hi>Ramhead</hi> may be cauſe of griefe,</l>
                  <l>Yet Nature hath this remedie found out,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould haue <hi>Lions</hi> hearts, to beare it ſtout,</l>
                  <l>And to defend and keepe the head from harme,</l>
                  <l>The Anagram of <hi>Ram,</hi> I finde, is <hi>Arm.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:13"/>
                  <l>Thus is a <hi>Ramhead</hi> arm'd againſt all feare,</l>
                  <l>He needs no helmet, or no head-piece weare.</l>
                  <l>To ſpeake more, in the plurall number, <hi>Rams,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It yeelds ſignifique warre like Anagrams,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Rams</hi> is <hi>Mars, Mars</hi> is the god of warre,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Rams</hi> is <hi>Arms, Arms</hi> warres munitions are;</l>
                  <l>And from the fierce encounters which they make,<note place="margin">Strange myſteries in the words Ram or Rams: the Rams the firſt run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at tilt and firſt teachers of warlike battel. Ioſephus Bella. lib. 3. cap. 9. Rams hornes the firſt trumpets.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our Tilts and Tourneys did beginnings take:</l>
                  <l>For as the <hi>Rams</hi> retire, and meet with rage,</l>
                  <l>So men doe in their warre-like equipage.</l>
                  <l>And long e're powder, (from hells damned den)</l>
                  <l>Was monſtrouſly produc'd, to murder men,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ram,</hi> an Engine call'd a <hi>Ram,</hi> did teach,</l>
                  <l>To batter downe a wall, or make a breach.</l>
                  <l>And now ſome places of defence, 'gainſt ſhot,</l>
                  <l>Haue (from the <hi>Ram</hi>) the name of <hi>Rampiers</hi> got.</l>
                  <l>Firſt warlike Trumpets that I e're heard nam'd,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Iericho,</hi> were all of <hi>Rams hornes</hi> fram'd:</l>
                  <l>For at the <hi>Ramshorne</hi> Trumpets fearefull blaſt,</l>
                  <l>Their curſed walls were ſuddenly downe caſt.</l>
                  <l>Thus is the <hi>Ram</hi> with many vertues ſtor'd,</l>
                  <l>And was in <hi>Egypt</hi> for a <hi>god</hi> ador'd:</l>
                  <l>And like a Captaine he the flocke doth leade,</l>
                  <l>As fits their Generall, their Prince or head.</l>
                  <l>Thus haue I prou'd a <hi>Sheepe,</hi> a beaſt of price,</l>
                  <l>Cleane, and reputed fit for ſacrifice:</l>
                  <l>And ſleeping, waking, early, or elſe late,</l>
                  <l>It ſtill doth chew the cud and ruminate.</l>
                  <l>Of all beaſts in the worlds circumference,</l>
                  <l>For meekneſſe, profit, and for innocence,</l>
                  <l>I haue approu'd a ſheepe moſt excellent,</l>
                  <l>That with leaſt coſt, doth giue man moſt content.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:13"/>
                  <l>There's ſuch inſtinct of Nature in the <hi>Lambe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By bleating, <hi>It,</hi> mongſt thouſands knowes the dam;<note place="margin">Agnus. Great knowledge in the Lambe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which the name of <hi>Agnoſcendo,</hi> knowing,</l>
                  <l>Is giuen to a <hi>Lambe,</hi> it's knowledge ſhowing.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="chronology">
               <p>But to conſider more ſeriouſly, the wonderfull bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the whole world hath had, and hath by ſheepe at this preſent, I thinke it not amiſſe to vſe the words of an ingenious and well affected Poet of our time, Maſter <hi>T. M.</hi> where he truly ſaith,</p>
               <p>No Ram no Lambe, no Lambe no Sheepe, no Sheepe no Wooll, no Wooll no Woolman, no Woolman no Spinner, no Spinner no Weauer, no Weauer no Cloth, no Cloth no Clothier, no Clothier no Clothworker, Fuller, Tucker, Shearman, Draper, or ſcarcely a rich Dier.</p>
               <p>And what infinite numbers of people rich and poore haue liued, and doe liue, hauing their whole dependance from the poore ſheepes backe, all men of iudgement will acknowledge; beſides, I thinke it not amiſſe to ſet downe the names of many worthy men, who haue beene free of London, of ſuch trades and myſteries whereof the <hi>ſheepe</hi> is the originall vnder God. And firſt, to begin with the Right Worſhipfull Company of <hi>Drapers,</hi> with the names of ſuch as haue borne the honourable Office and Dignitie of <hi>Lord Maior</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> with their pious deeds, and diuers other perſons of the ſaid Company, their names, and memorable charities, with the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Worſhipfull Company of <hi>Clothwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi> And firſt, I begin with the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1189. In the beginning of the raigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, Sir <hi>Henrie Fitz Allen</hi> Draper, was the
<pb facs="tcp:18889:14"/>firſt Lord Maior of <hi>London,</hi> who continued in that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie twentie foure yeares together, till the fourteenth yeare of King <hi>Iohn</hi> 1212. when he died, he was a worthy Benefactor to his Company, and gaue houſes to the vſe of the poore, in the pariſh of Saint <hi>Marie Bothaw</hi> in <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke</hi> ward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1252. <hi>Iohn Talaſon</hi> Draper, Maior.</p>
               <p>1253. <hi>Richard Hardell</hi> Draper, ſixe yeares Maior.</p>
               <p>1330. Sir <hi>Iohn Pultney</hi> Draper, two yeares Maior.</p>
               <p>1332. <hi>Iohn Preſton</hi> Draper, Maior.</p>
               <p>1333. Sir <hi>Iohn Pultney,</hi> Maior.</p>
               <p>1336.<note place="margin">Many of theſe men did good and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deeds, but they did them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in their liues time.</note> Sir <hi>Iohn Pultney</hi> the fourth time Lord Maior, he built a Chappell in <hi>Pauls,</hi> where he lies buried: he alſo built Saint <hi>Laurence Pultney</hi> Church, and the Church of little <hi>Alhalowes,</hi> and the Church called the <hi>Friers</hi> in <hi>Couentrie:</hi> he gaue to the poore of Saint <hi>Giles</hi> in the fields, to the poore priſoners in the <hi>Fleet</hi> and <hi>Newgate,</hi> ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to each yearely for euer, beſides many other deeds of charitie which he did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1363. <hi>Stephen Candiſh</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1367. <hi>Iames Andrew</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1381. <hi>Iohn Northampton</hi> Draper two yeares Maior.</p>
               <p>1391. <hi>Iohn Hinde</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1402. <hi>Iohn Walcot</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1404. <hi>Iohn Hinde</hi> the ſecond time Maior, he newly built the Church of Saint <hi>Swithin</hi> neere London ſtone.</p>
               <p>1413. Sir <hi>William Cromer</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1415. Sir <hi>Nicholas Wotton</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1423. <hi>William Cromer</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1427. <hi>Iohn Gedney</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1430. <hi>Nicholas Wotton</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1433. <hi>Iohn Brockle</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:14"/>
               <p> 1441. <hi>Robert Clopton</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1445. Sir <hi>Simon Eyre</hi> Draper Maior, he built Leaden Hall for a Garnerie for the Citie, and gaue fiue thouſand Markes to charitable vſes.</p>
               <p>1447. Sir <hi>Iohn Gedney</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1453. Sir <hi>Iohn Norman</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1458. Sir <hi>Thomas Scot</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1462. Sir <hi>Thomas Cooke</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1464. Sir <hi>Ralph Ioſlin</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1474. Sir <hi>Robert Drope</hi> Draper, Maior; he lieth buried in Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> Church in Cornhill London: he gaue towards poore maides marriages of that pariſh twentie pound, and to the poore of that ward ten pound, and three hundred ſhirts and ſmockes, and a hundred gownes of Broadcloth.</p>
               <p>1476. Sir <hi>Ralph Ioſlin</hi> Draper, the ſecond time Maior.</p>
               <p>1479. Sir <hi>Bartholomew Iames</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1481. Sir <hi>William Harriot</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1484. Sir <hi>William Stocker</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1489. Sir <hi>William White</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1503. Sir <hi>William Capell</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1507. <hi>Laurence Aylmer</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1509. Sir <hi>William Capell</hi> the ſecond time Maior.</p>
               <p>1511. Sir <hi>Roger Achley</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1514. Sir <hi>George Monox</hi> Draper Maior, he repaired the ruinated Church at <hi>Walthamſtow</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and erected a Free Schoole there, and thirteene Almeshouſes for aged people, alſo he built a long Timber Cawſway ouer the Marſhes from <hi>Walthamſtow</hi> to <hi>Locke Bridge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1520. Sir <hi>Iohn Bruges</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1521. Sir <hi>Iohn Milbourne</hi> Draper Maior, he built 14. Almeshouſes for 14. aged poore people, neere the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:18889:15"/>
                  <hi>Lumleys</hi> houſe in the croſſed or crooched Friers, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to each, two ſhillings foure pence monthly for euer.</p>
               <p>1524. Sir <hi>William Bailie</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1528. Sir <hi>Iohn Rudſton</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1533. Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Askew</hi> Draper Maior, he paied largely to the building of eight Almeshouſes in <hi>Beech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> London, for eight poore Widowes of his company.</p>
               <p>1540. Sir <hi>William Roch</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1560. Sir <hi>William Cheſter</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1565. Sir <hi>Richard Champion</hi> Draper Maior, a good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor to the poore of Saint <hi>Dunſtans</hi> in the Eaſt, and to the poore in Saint <hi>Edmunds</hi> in Lumbard ſtreet he gaue fiftie foure ſhillings yearely in bread for euer, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gifts.</p>
               <p>1578. Sir <hi>Richard Pipe</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1580. Sir <hi>Iohn Branch</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1584. Sir <hi>Thomas Pulliſon</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1588. Sir <hi>Martin Calthrop</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1614. Sir <hi>Thomas Hayes</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1615. Sir <hi>Iohn Iolls</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1621. Sir <hi>Edward Barkham</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
               <p>1623. <hi>Martin Lumley</hi> Draper Maior.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="list_of_actions">
               <head>Theſe good deeds following were done by others of the ſaid Company, who were not Lord Maiors.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOhn Holmes</hi> Draper, gaue his houſe to the poore in Saint <hi>Sepulchers</hi> pariſh for euer, the yeerely rent of it being thirtie two pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Ruſſell</hi> Draper, gaue eightie pound to Schooles, and to other pious vſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Quarles</hi> Draper, gaue ſixe pound a yeere for euer
<pb facs="tcp:18889:15"/>to be giuen to the poore in bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Dummer</hi> Draper, gaue to the poore thirteene pound eighteene ſhillings foure pence, yeerly for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen Clun</hi> Draper, gaue to the poore fiue and twentie pound yeerly for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Parker</hi> Draper, towards the maintenance of Preachers at Saint <hi>Antlins</hi> ſixe pounds yeerly for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Skeet</hi> Draper, gaue to the Hoſpitals at London three hundred pound, and to foure poore ſchollers at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford fiue pound a piece, and the like to foure poore ſchollers at Cambridge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henrie Butler</hi> Draper, gaue to Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall ten pound, to <hi>Chriſt Church,</hi> Saint <hi>Bartholomewes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> fiue pounds to each.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Hall</hi> Draper, gaue to <hi>Chriſts</hi> Hoſpitall ten pound, to Saint <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> and Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall three pound to each.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Church</hi> Draper, gaue to <hi>Christs</hi> Hoſpitall and to <hi>Bridewell,</hi> to each ten pound, and to the Hoſpitals of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> to either fiue pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humphrey Fox</hi> Draper, gaue to <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fiftie pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edmund Hill</hi> Draper, gaue to the poore of Saint <hi>Andrew Vnder ſhaft</hi> fiftie two pound, anno 1609.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Gilborne</hi> Draper, gaue foure markes the yeere for euer to the poore of Saint <hi>Katherine</hi> Chriſt Church neere Aldegate, &amp; twentie pound he gaue to build a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery in the ſame Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Quarles</hi> Draper, gaue to the poore of Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in the poore in Bredſtreet ward, fiftie pound to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed yeerly in bread for euer.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Richard Goddard</hi> Draper, and Alderman, gaue to
<pb facs="tcp:18889:16"/>the Hoſpitall of <hi>Bridewell</hi> two hundred pound.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Benedict Barnham</hi> Draper, gaue for the reliefe of poore priſoners, in the ſeueral priſons of London, 50. <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Iames Deane,</hi> Draper and Alderman, gaue to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Hoſpitals in London, a hundred and thirtie pound, and to ſundry priſons ſeuentie pound.</p>
               <p>Lady <hi>Bainham,</hi> ſometimes an Aldermans wife of the Drapers Company, gaue to the poore of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ten pound yeerely for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lancelot Thomſon</hi> Draper, gaue to the pariſh of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> in Cornhill, twentie pound for fiue Sermons, and a hundred pound to the poore of the Drapers Company, and fiue pound yeerely to be beſtowed by them in fire and bread on the poore of that pariſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Shore</hi> Draper, gaue fifteene pound to build a Church porch at Saint <hi>Mildreds</hi> in the Powltrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Calthrop</hi> Draper, built the Bricke wall betwixt the Hoſpitals of Chriſts Church and Saint <hi>Bartholomew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Chertſey</hi> Draper, gaue to the Hoſpitals twentie pound, and to other charitable vſes a hundred pound.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Henrie Woolaſton</hi> Draper, gaue to Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall fourtie pound, with other charitable beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences.</p>
               <p>Theſe memorable and pious workes, (with many more then my weake capacitie can collect and reckon) haue beene done by the Drapers or Clothſellers, which doth approue the ſheepe to be a thriuing, happy, and a moſt profitable beaſt. Now to ſpeake ſomwhat of the Right Worſhipfull Company of Clothworkers.</p>
               <p>Anno Domini 1559. Sir <hi>William Hewet</hi> Clothworker, Lord Maior.</p>
               <p>1570. Sir <hi>Rowland Heyward</hi> Clothworker, Lord Maior.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:16"/>
               <p> 1574. Sir <hi>Iames Hawes</hi> Clothworker Lord Maior.</p>
               <p>1583. Sir <hi>Edward Osborne</hi> Clothworker Lord Maior.</p>
               <p>1594. Sir <hi>Iohn Spencer</hi> Clothworker Lord Maior.<note place="margin">K. Iames (our moſt gracious Soueraign was made a free bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Clothwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Sir Iohn Wats being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior, who feaſted his Maieſtie, Sir Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Stone Knight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then Maſter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as which time the King gaue a gift of a. brace of Bucks to the ſaid Company yeerly for euer, to be ſpent at their feaſt in their Hall.</note>
               </p>
               <p>1596. Sir <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> Clothworker L. Maior, gaue to the Hoſpitals in London and the Suburbs 120. <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>1599. Sir <hi>Nicholas Moſley</hi> Clothworker L. Maior.</p>
               <p>1606. Sir <hi>Iohn Wats</hi> Clothworker Lord Maior, gaue to <hi>Chriſt Church</hi> Hoſpitall ten pound, and to the Hoſpitall of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> in <hi>Southwarke</hi> twentie pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Farringdon</hi> Clothworker and Alderman, gaue to the ſeuerall Hoſpitals in London and the Suburbs 66. pound, 13. ſhillings foure pence.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>William Stone</hi> Clothworker, gaue to the ſeuerall priſons in London 50. pound.</p>
               <p>Lady <hi>Barbara Stone,</hi> wife to the forenamed Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Stone,</hi> gaue to the Hoſpitall of Chriſts Church one hundred pounds.</p>
               <p>Lady <hi>Spencer,</hi> wife to Sir <hi>Iohn Spencer</hi> Clothworker, gaue to the ſeuerall Hoſpitals ſeuentie pound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Lambe</hi> Eſquire, free of the company of Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workers, &amp; one of the Gentlemen of the Chappel to king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, built a free Grammar Schoole at <hi>Sutton Valence</hi> in Kent, (where he was borne) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing yeerely for euer to the Maſter of the ſaid Scchoole twentie pound, and to the Vſher ten pound: alſo he built 6. Almeshouſes there, with gardens &amp; orch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and 10. <abbr>l.</abbr> yeerly to each of them for euer. Beſides, he gaue to the free ſchoole at <hi>Maidſtone</hi> in Kent 10. pound yeerly for euer, which he appointed to be beſtowed only vpon poore children, who were deſtitute of friends and ſuccourleſſe. Alſo he beſtowed three hundred pound for the vſe of decayed Clothiers in the Countie of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,</hi> and in the townes of <hi>Bridgenorth</hi> and <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:17"/>Moreouer, hee built two Conduits in London, one at Holbourne Bridge, and the other on the Hill towards New-Gate, both of which coſt 1500. pounds; at which time he gaue 120. new Pailes to ſo many poore women, to beare water withall: Moreouer, he gaue thirtie pound a yeere to his Company for euer, and 4. pounds yeerely to a Miniſter for foure Sermons, and thirty pound yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for euer to be beſtowed on twelue poore men, and twelue poore women; each of them to haue a Freeze Gowne, one Lockrom ſhirt or ſmock, one paire of winter ſhooes; which Gift is yeerely diſtributed on the firſt of October; he alſo gaue to the Poore of Saint <hi>Giles</hi> Pariſh without Cripplegate, fifteene pound: To the Poore of the Company of <hi>Stationers,</hi> he gaue ſixe pounds, thirteen ſhillings, foure pence yeerely for euer, to be beſtowed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Fry day in the Pariſh of S. <hi>Faiths,</hi> on twelue poore people, twelue pence in bread, and twelue pence in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. He gaue to Chriſts Hoſpitall ſixe pounds yeerely for euer and 100. pounds in ready money preſent; Hee gaue to S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall 4. pounds yeerely for euer: and to poore Maids marriages he gaue 20. pounds: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Newgate, Ludgate, the two Comptors, in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, the Marſhalſea, the Kings-Bench, and the White Lyon, had all moſt louing taſts of his Charitable liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and in concluſion, he gaue 108. Gownes to poore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged people at his Funerall.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>This was a <hi>Lambe,</hi> whoſe like was neuer any:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loue and pitty ſed and cloth'd ſo many:</l>
                  <l>And 'tis no doubt, but theſe good deeds of his,</l>
                  <l>Did helpe to lift his Soule to endleſſe Bliſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Iohn Berriman</hi> of <hi>Biſhops Taunton</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Deuon-ſhire, Clothier, and free Draper of London,
<pb facs="tcp:18889:17"/>gaue to the Hoſpitall of Chriſt-Church, 100. pounds: to S. Bartholomewes, 5. pounds: to S. Thomas Hoſpitall, 6. pounds, to Bridewell 40. Shillings: and to the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of Bethlem, 50. pounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Blundell,</hi> Clothier, gaue to Chriſt-Church Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, 500 pounds: to Saint Bartholomewes Hoſpitall, 250. pounds: to Saint Thomas Hoſpitall 250. pounds: to Bridewell, 8. pounds yeerely foreuer: to the Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church at <hi>Tiuerton</hi> (where he was borne) 50. pounds: towards the mending of High-wayes, 100. pounds: to the twelue Companies in <hi>London,</hi> to euery of them 150. pound: to poore Maides marriages in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerton,</hi> 400. pound: to the poore at <hi>Exeſter,</hi> he gaue 900. pound: to build a Grammer-ſchoole at <hi>Tiuerton,</hi> 2400. pounds: and after laid out by his Executors, 1000. pound: to the Schoole-maſter 50. pounds yeerely for euer: to the Vſher 13. pound 6. ſhillings 8. pence yeerely: to the Clarke 40. ſhillings yeerely: to place foure poore boyes yeerely Aprentiſes, 20. pounds <hi>per annum:</hi> to keepe three Schollers at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and three at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> 2000. <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Chilcot,</hi> Seruant to the aforeſaid M. <hi>Blundell,</hi> gaue to Chriſts Hoſpitall 100. pound towards a meaner Schoole, to haue Children taught, to be apt for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Grammer-Schoole: he gaue 400. pound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it: he gaue 90. pound, allowing the Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter yeerely 20. pound, the Clarke 3. pound, and toward Reparations, 40. ſhillings <hi>per annum:</hi> to fifteene poore men he gaue 16. pounds, 10. ſhillings a yeere for euer: to fifteen poore labouring men 15. pound: to fifteene poore people weekely, ſix pence each, for euer: to mend the Church at <hi>Tiuerton,</hi> 19. pound, 10. ſhillings: to mend High-waies, 10. pounds: and to other charitable vſes, more then is mentioned.</p>
               <p>Thus hath it pleaſed God, that theſe men (whoſe trades
<pb facs="tcp:18889:18"/>and liuings were deriued from the poore Sheepes backe) haue not onely growne to great wealth, and places of Honour, but haue bin alſo great Inſtruments of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties mercy, in relieuing the needy and impotent members of Chriſt: and ſhould I reckon vp the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of profits that ariſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Beaſt, to Graziers, Butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Skinners, Glouers, Felmongers, Leatherſellers, Felt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, Taylors, &amp; an infinite number of other Trades and Functions, who could not liue, or els liue very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without this Commodity. I ſay, ſhould I write of theſe things in particular, my worke would neuer bee done in generall.</p>
               <p>Wooll hath beene formerly in ſuch eſteeme in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that in a Parliament holden the 36. of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, the King had his Subiects paide him in wooll; and before that, in the 11. yeere of his Raigne, is was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be tranſported out of this Kingdome; and then did Strangers come ouer hither, from diuers parts beyond the Seas, who were Fullers, Weauers, and Clothwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, whom the King entertained, and bare all their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges out of his Exchequer: at which time, the Staples, or places of marchandiſe for Woolls, were kept at diuers places of this Land at once; as at <hi>Newcaſtle, Yorke, Lincoln, Canterbury, Norwich, Weſtminſter, Chicheſter, Wincheſter, Exeſter, Briſtoll,</hi> and <hi>Carmarthen:</hi> by which may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued what a great commodity wooll was in thoſe daies. But in the 6. yeere of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, the King ſent certaine Ships out of <hi>Cotſwold</hi> in Gloceſter ſhire, into <hi>Spaine,</hi> the encreaſe of which ſo inriched the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with our wooll, that euer ſince, it hath bin in the leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in England: neuer theleſſe, as it is, it is the meanes of life and maintenance for many hundred thouſands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANd now from ſolid Proſe I will abſtaine</l>
                  <l>To pleaſant Poetrie, and mirth againe.<note place="margin">Here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a touch of paltry Scabbed infectious kind of Sheepe, which I thinke fit to place by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the lagge end of my Booke, as farre as I can from the clean, ſound, &amp; profitable Sheepe before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for feare the bad ſhould infect the good.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Fable of the Golden Fleece began,</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe Sheepe did yeeld ſuch ſtore of Gold to Man:</l>
                  <l>For he that hath great ſtore of woolly fleeces,</l>
                  <l>May (when he pleaſe) haue ſtore of golden peeces.</l>
                  <l>Thus many a poore man dying, hath left a Sonne,</l>
                  <l>That hath tranſſorm'd the <hi>Fleece</hi> to Gold, like <hi>Iaſon:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And heere's a myſtery profound and deepe,</l>
                  <l>There's ſundry ſorts of <hi>Mutton,</hi> are no <hi>Sheepe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lac'd Mutton, which let out themſelues to hire,</l>
                  <l>Like Hackneys, who'le be fir'd, before they tire.</l>
                  <l>The man or men which for ſuch Mutton hungers,</l>
                  <l>Are (by their Corporation) Mutton-mongers:</l>
                  <l>Which is a brotherhood ſo large and great,</l>
                  <l>That if they had a Hall, I would intreat</l>
                  <l>To be their Clarke, or keeper of accounts,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew them vnto what their charge amounts;</l>
                  <l>My braines in numbring then wound grow ſo quicke,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould be maſter of Arithmeticke:</l>
                  <l>All States, Degrees, and Trades, both bad and good,</l>
                  <l>Afford ſome members of this Brotherhood:</l>
                  <l>Great therefore needs muſt be their multitude,</l>
                  <l>When euery man may to the Trade intrude:</l>
                  <l>It it no free dome, yet theſe men are free,</l>
                  <l>Not ſauers, but moſt liberall ſpenders be:</l>
                  <l>For this is one thing that doth them bewitch,</l>
                  <l>That by their trading they waxe ſeldome rich:</l>
                  <l>The value of this <hi>Mutton</hi> to ſet foorth,</l>
                  <l>The fleſh doth coſt more than the broth is worth:</l>
                  <l>They all are <hi>Ewes,</hi> yet are exceeding <hi>Ramiſh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And will be dainty fed, whoſ 'euer famiſh.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:19"/>
                  <l>Nor are they <hi>mark'd</hi> for any man, or no man,</l>
                  <l>As mine, or thine, but euery mans in common,</l>
                  <l>Fine <hi>heads,</hi> and <hi>neckes,</hi> and <hi>breaſts,</hi> they yeeld ſome ſtoree,</l>
                  <l>But ſcarcely one good <hi>liuer</hi> in nine ſcore:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>liuers</hi> being bad, 'tis vnderſtood,</l>
                  <l>The veines are fild with putrified blood,</l>
                  <l>Which makes them ſubiect to the ſcab, and then</l>
                  <l>They proue moſt dang rous diet vnto men.</l>
                  <l>And then the prouerbe proues no lie or mocke,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One ſcabbed ſheepe's enough to ſpoyle a flocke.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But yet for all this, there is many a Gull,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loues Mutton well, and dips his bread i'the wooll.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And were a man put to his choyce to keepe,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſaid, <hi>a Shrew is better then a Sheepe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But if a man be yok'd with ſuch an <hi>Ewe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She may be both a ſcabbed <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Shrew.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And he that is ſo match'd, his life may well</l>
                  <l>Compared be vnto an earthly hell.</l>
                  <l>But to my Theame which I wrote of before,</l>
                  <l>I at this <hi>Mutton</hi> muſt haue one cut more.</l>
                  <l>Theſe kinde of <hi>Sheepe</hi> haue all the world o're growne,</l>
                  <l>And ſeldome doe weare fleeces of their owne:</l>
                  <l>For they from ſundry men their pelts can pull,</l>
                  <l>Whereby they keepe themſelues as warme as wooll.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, in colours, and in ſhape, they varie</l>
                  <l>Quite from all profitable ſheepe contrarie:</l>
                  <l>White, Blacke, Greene, Tawny, Purple, Red, and Blue,</l>
                  <l>Beyond the Raine-bow for their change of hue:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camelion</hi> like in alteration,</l>
                  <l>But, that bare Aire they cannot liue vpon.</l>
                  <l>The Moones mutation's, not more manifold,</l>
                  <l>Silke, Veluet, Tiſſue, Cloth, and cloth of God:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18889:19"/>
                  <l>Theſe are the <hi>Sheepe</hi> that <hi>Golden fleeces</hi> weare,<note place="margin">They are as ſoft as Silke-wormes.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who robe themſelues with others <hi>wooll</hi> or <hi>haire:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And it may be, 'twas ſuch a <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>Fleece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Iaſon</hi> brought from <hi>Cholcos,</hi> into <hi>Greece.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were it no more but ſo, I dare be bold</l>
                  <l>To thinke this Land doth many <hi>Iaſons</hi> hold:</l>
                  <l>Who neuer durſt to paſſe a dang'rous waue,</l>
                  <l>Yet may (with eaſe) ſuch <hi>Golden fleeces</hi> haue.</l>
                  <l>Too much of one thing's good for nought (they ſay)</l>
                  <l>Ile therefore take this needleſſe diſh away:</l>
                  <l>For ſhould I too much, of <hi>Lac'd Mutton</hi> write,</l>
                  <l>I may o're come my Readers ſtomacke quite.</l>
                  <l>Once more vnto the good <hi>Sheepe</hi> Ile retire,</l>
                  <l>And ſo my Booke ſhall to it's end expire:</l>
                  <l>Although it be not found in Ancient writers,</l>
                  <l>I finde all <hi>Muttone-aters</hi> are <hi>ſheepe-biters.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in ſome places I haue heard and ſeene,</l>
                  <l>That curriſh <hi>ſheepe-biters</hi> haue <hi>hanged</hi> beene,</l>
                  <l>If any kinde of <hi>Tike</hi> ſhould ſnarle or whine,</l>
                  <l>Or bite, or woorry this poore <hi>Sheepe</hi> of mine,</l>
                  <l>Why let them barke and bite, and ſpend their breath,</l>
                  <l>Ile neuer wiſh them a <hi>ſheepe-biters</hi> death.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Sheepe</hi> will haue them know, her Innocence</l>
                  <l>Shall liue, in ſpight of their maleuolence:</l>
                  <l>I wiſh them keepe themſelues and me from paine,</l>
                  <l>And bite ſuch <hi>Sheepe</hi> as cannot bite againe.</l>
                  <l>For if they ſnap at mine, I haue a pen,</l>
                  <l>That (like a truſtie Dogge) ſhall bite agen.</l>
                  <l>And in Concluſion, this I humbly craue,</l>
                  <l>That euery one the honeſtie may haue,</l>
                  <l>That when our fraile mortalitie is paſt,</l>
                  <l>We may be the good Shepheards ſheepe at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:18889:20"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
